Guide to the University Heights Time Capsule MC.269
New York University Archives
University Heights Time Capsule
1891-1964
1956-1964
New York University Archives
New York University. University Heights
MC.269
3.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, 1 flat box, 1 CD box, 1 flat-file folder, and 1 custom-size time capsule
10 sound tape reels
This collection consists of a time capsule assembled in the early 1960s by members of the Perstare et Praestare Society, an academic honor society for NYU students at the University Heights Campus. The collection includes the titanium time capsule container as well as the items selected for inclusion. These items include a variety of NYU-produced publications, course syllabi, audio recordings, and ephemera documenting the different student populations, extracurricular student activities such as student productions of dramatic works, and notable campus events such as commencement. The collection also reflects the larger political climate of the early 1960s, through materials like election leaflets, publications concerning the John F. Kennedy presidential administration and his assassination, and ephemera from the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) documenting on-campus civil rights. This collection also includes numerous programs for ceremonies for the Hall of Fame of Great Americans, an outdoor sculpture garden on campus featuring portrait busts of noted artists, intellectuals, and politicians.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Documentation concerning the full chain of provenance for this time capsule and the materials included in it is incomplete. The time capsule was identified as part of the New York University Archives collection in 1993; the accession number associated is 2017.008.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Original order is unknown.
Historical Note
This time capsule was assembled through the efforts of multiple people. David Fleischmann (UC '60), convened a committee of members of the Perstare et Praestare Society, an academic honor society for NYU students, to select the objects included in the time capsule. Dr. John P. Nielsen of the department of metallurgy and materials sciences assisted the committee, and Dr. Harold Margolin, professor of metallurgical engineering, designed the time capsule itself. The time capsule was made of titanium and filled with helium before being sealed. It was buried in 1964 on the University Heights campus although more specific information concerning when and where the burial took place has not yet been recorded.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of a time capsule assembled in the early 1960s by members of the Perstare et Praestare Society, an academic honor society for NYU students at the University Heights Campus. The collection includes the titanium time capsule container as well as the items selected for inclusion. These items include a variety of NYU-produced publications, course syllabi, audio recordings, and ephemera documenting the different student populations, extracurricular student activities such as student productions of dramatic works, and notable campus events such as commencement. The collection also reflects the larger political climate of the early 1960s, through materials like election leaflets, publications concerning the John F. Kennedy presidential administration and his assassination, and ephemera from the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) documenting on-campus civil rights. This collection also includes numerous programs for ceremonies for the Hall of Fame of Great Americans, an outdoor sculpture garden on campus featuring portrait busts of noted artists, intellectuals, and politicians.
Time capsules; Student activities.; Students -- Political activity -- United States.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963
- Student Nonviolence Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Press Release about Reverend Ashton Bryant Jones Arrest, 1963-11-20 (Box 1)
- Gambit, Spring 1964 (Box 1)
- Senior Class Night Exercises Program, 1964-06-08 (Box 1)
- Baccalaureate Program, 1964-06-07 (Box 1)
- Commencement Program, 1964-06-10 (Box 1)
- 2 Issues of the Newman newsletter from the Newman Club of NYU, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
- Ticket to Baccalaureate Service, 1964-06-07 (Box 1)
- Promotional Brochure for the School of Engineering and Science, undated (Box 1)
- Issue of The Korean Report (not an NYU publication), 1963-10-1963-11 (Box 1)
- SNCC Schedule for Conference on Food and Jobs held at Howard University, 1963 (Box 1)
- SNCC Press Release about Voter Registration Drive in North Carolina, 1963-11-20 (Box 1)
- SNCC Press Release about Keynote Speakers James Baldwin and Bayard Rustin at Conference on Food and Jobs, 1963 (Box 1)
- Spring NYU Sport Calendars, 1964 (Box 1)
- Daniel J. Stark Classics 63 exam (NO), 1963 (Box 1)
- New York Times Magazine, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
- Life Magazine: John F. Kennedy Memorial Edition, 1963 (Box 3)
- Look Magazine, 1962-01-02 (Box 3)
- SNCC Press Release about Pine Bluff Movement Protest Against McDonalds, undated (Box 1)
- Flier from Scheuer for Congress Committee, Bronx, indicating NYT endorsement for Scheuer, 1964 (Box 1)
- JFK Commemorative Postage stamps, 5 cents, circa 1963 (Box 1)
- Heights Young Democrats Publication, The Monitor, undated (Box 1)
- New York Times (full issue), 1964-04-06 (Box 3)
- New York Post, 1964-03-05 (Box 3)
- Square Journal (NYU publication), 1964-05-14 (Box 3)
- Daily News, 1964-04-07 (Box 3)
- Envelope from the Permanent Mission of the USSR to the United Nations, sent to Stephen Carson of the Heights Daily News, containing various NYU publications, plus Soviet publications in English: issue of USSR Soviet Life Today; Several issues of a newspaper titled Soviet Weekly; Undated unattributed typescript titled "Brief History" (appears to be of the Soviet Union); booklet by P. Mstislavsky titled "For the Good of All", 1963 (Box 3)
- University College of Arts and Science (UCAS) Bulletin, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- Advanced Study at NYU Bulletin, undated (Box 1)
- Blank Sheet of Lined Notebook Paper, undated (Box 1)
- Program for Department of Speech Production of H.M.S. Pinafore, 1964 (Box 1)
- Student Directory, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- Hall of Fame for Great Americans at New York University, edited by Theodore Morello, 1962 (Box 1)
- Division of General Education Course Bulletin, Spring 1964 (Box 1)
- Program from Performance of The Flies by Jean Paul Sartre (Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Program from Performance of Gordon A by John Rissmer (Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Senior Class Night Exercises Program, 1960-06-06 (Box 1)
- Program from Performance of The Boys from Syracuse by Rodgers and Hart (Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- JCF News, 1957-11-27 (Box 1)
- Flier for NYU University Heights Opera Workshop Performance of Engelbert Humperdinck's Hansel and Gretel, undated (Box 1)
- The Violet, 1891 (Box 1)
- New York University Alumni News, 1964-04-1964-05 (Box 1)
- Dean's Greetings and Time Capsule, with Typed Address Given on Decoration Day, Addressed to "My Dear Reader," and written by Dean J. W. Knedler, circa 1964 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook Pages: Circular of the Faculty of Science and Letters of the University of the City of New York, During Financial Crisis when Faculty Administered the budget; Photographs of student life, with captions, 1852, 1960 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook Page: Map of University Heights campus by Vaux and Co., 1893 (Flat-file-folder 1 Right)
- Fliers for Campus Events from Student Center Policy Board (SCPB), 1962-1964 (Box 1)
- Freshman Convocation Program for UCES, 1962-09 (Box 1)
- 2 Copies of the Bristol Journal, published by members of the Bristol Pre-Medical and Pre-Dental Society of University College (1 with button that says "I'm on the Rockefeller Team"), 1962-04 (Box 1)
- Heights Daily News (35 issues), 1955-1956, 1959-1964 (Box 1)
- Fliers for Congressman James C. Healey Re-election, circa 1960-1964 (Box 1)
- Bronx Democrat (Not NYU-produced Political Newspaper, 2 Issues), 1964-05-1965-06 (Box 1)
- Herald-Tribune Guide to the 1964 World's Fair, 1964-04-19 (Box 3)
- Principal Addresses Delivered by General de Gaulle, President of the French Republic, During his Official Visit to Mexico (in English), 1964-03 (Box 1)
- NYU Press Release Announcing University College of Arts and Science Dean's List, 1963-12-12 (Box 1)
- Resident Lists for Silver Residence Center, Gould Hall for Women and Lowe Hall for Men (Alphabetical List of Students with Room Number, Class, and City/State of origin), Spring 1964 (Box 1)
- School of Engineering List of Male Transfer Students, undated (Box 1)
- List of Freshman Boys for School of Engineering (Student Name, Parents' Names, and Parents' Addresses), undated (Box 1)
- List of Transfer Boys for University College of Arts and Science (Parents' Names and Addresses), undated (Box 1)
- List of Transfer Girls for University College of Arts and Science (Parents' Names and Addresses), undated (Box 1)
- List of Incoming Freshman Girls to University College of Arts and Science (Parents' Names and Addresses), undated (Box 1)
- List of Incoming Freshman Boys to University College of Arts and Science (Parents' Names and Addresses), undated (Box 1)
- "Here's New York University" Pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
- "Go Fraternity" Rushing Brochure, 1963 (Box 1)
- Syllabus for English U41.0057 (Victorian Literature) Taught by Professor Dan H. Laurence, Spring 1964 (Box 1)
- Syllabus for English U41.0061 (British Literature Since 1890) Taught by Dan H. Laurence, Fall 1963 (Box 1)
- Syllabu for English U41.0041,42 (The Novel), 1964-06 (Box 1)
- Blank Copy of Questionnaire for Students Applying to English U41.0047 (Victorian Humor Independent Reading Course), 1964 (Box 1)
- Syllabus for English U29.0034 (Comparative Literature), 1964-07 (Box 1)
- Assignment List for English 63 and 64 taught by Professors Allen and Miller, undated (Box 1)
- British Lit since 1890 Overview of Ulysses, 1964 (Box 1)
- "The Honors Program at University College" with Professor Laurence's Name Written at Top, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- Blank Final Exams for Professor Dan H. Laurence's English U41.0062 and U41.0058, 1964-04 (Box 1)
- Advance Announcement: Associate in Arts Degree Program for Adults for Division of General Education, circa 1964 (Box 1)
- Perspective, vol. 1 no. 1, Fall 1963 (Box 1)
- NYU Notebook, 1964-01 (Box 1)
- Page of Time Magazine Depicting Tech II or Other Breuer Building, 1963-05-24 (Box 1)
- Society for the Libraries of NYU Bulletin, Summer 1963 and Winter 1964 (Box 1)
- NYU Weekly Calendar, 1964-05 (Box 1)
- Hand-drawn Program of Play Presented by the Director's Workshop at the Department of Speech and Drama (Prison Scene from The Threepenny Opera), undated (Box 1)
- Flier for Performance of The Threepenny Opera Sponsored by the NYU Heights German Club, undated (Box 1)
- School of Engineering Technical Papers, Publications, and Talks, 1963 (Box 1)
- School of Engineering and Science Bulletin, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- On the Square, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- New York Journal American (not an NYU publication) Issue on the Bronx ("Distributed to Bronx schoolchildren as a service by Sachs Quality Tours"), 1964-01-19 (Box 3)
- New York Times Clipping: "Waitress Who Stayed for Dinner in 1934 Retires" (About Woman Retiring from NYU Faculty Club), 1964-05-06 (Box 1)
- Perstare et Praestare Letters (One Inviting Reader to Ceremony of burial of time capsule; Other Inviting Reader to Spring Induction Dinner), 1964-05 (Box 1)
- Promotional Publication for the Peace Corps (not NYU publication), undated (Box 1)
- Program for the Induction of the Thomas Edison Bust in the Hall of Fame for Great Americans, 1961-06-04 (Box 1)
- "UN on Campus" (not an NYU publication), Fall 1958 (Box 1)
- Flier Advertising John Mason Brown Speaking at Heights Campus, 1960-02-19 (Box 1)
- Program for The Skin of Our Teeth (Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Program for Senior Class Night Exercises, 1961-06-05 (Box 1)
- Program for Semi-annual Perstare and Praestare Dinner, 1962-12-23 (Box 1)
- Program for The Male Animal (Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Student Center Policy Board Meeting Minutes, 1958-10-07 (Box 1)
- Typewritten and Annotated Memorandum from The Historian Magazine Staff Discussing Upcoming Themes and Financing Issues, Fall 1959 (Box 1)
- Program for NYU University Heights Opera Workshop Performance of Aida, undated (Box 1)
- Program for The Adding Machine (Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Student Governing Board Bulletin, 1961-02 (Box 1)
- Program for Concert by Juilliard Students, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
- Page 2 of a Final Examination for Speech 52, undated (Box 1)
- Program for Billy Budd (Green Room Honor Sociey and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Flier for Performance of The Dragon by James Taylor (NYU Opera Workshop, Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Chaucer Parody and Handwritten Notes, undated (Box 1)
- Issue of Scope 60; Candidates' Statements for Student Office Candidates, 1960 (Box 1)
- Dedication Program for Bust of Henry David Thoreau in Hall of Fame, 1962-05-06 (Box 1)
- Program for Dedication of Busts of Josiah Willard Gibbs and George Westinghouse in Hall of Fame, 1957-12-01 (Box 1)
- New York University Radio Network Program Guide, Fall 1963 (Box 1)
- Report of the President of NYU, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Regarding Perstare et Praestare Addressed to Dave Fleishmann (One Indicating that the Bun had been Stolen (Again)), 1959-05 (Box 1)
- Program for Baby Carson (Green Room Honor Society and Hall of Fame Players), undated (Box 1)
- Palisades Handbook, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- Prestare et Praestare Correspondence between Stephen Carson and Dave Fleischmann, 1964 (Box 1)
- Invitation to Dedication of Julius Silver Residence Center, 1963 (Box 1)
- Letter to Stephen Carson (Co-editor of Heights Daily News)about Plagiarism, 1964-02-19 (Box 1)
- Alumni Appeal Letter from President James M. Hester, 1962-11-16 (Box 1)
- Announcement of Graduate Services for the 128th Commencement Season, 1960 (Box 1)
- NYU Directory of Undergraduate Student Leaders, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
- NYT Clipping: "President's Trip Arouses Texans," "Kennedy Spares the Life of 55 Pound Gift Turkey", 1963-11-20 (Box 1)
- "New Purpose, New Progress: The Kennedy Administration in Words and Pictures" (not NYU), circa 1962-1963 (Box 1)
- Postcards, undated (Box 1)
- DNC Brochure: "All Americans Move Forward: Democratic Action for Civil Rights" (Partial Listing of African American Appointees in the Kennedy Administration), circa 1961-1963 (Box 1)
- USA 1 Pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
- Program Mailing from US National Student Association for "Fast for Freedom Food" Event, 1964-01-10 (Box 1)
- DNC Brochure: "Why Be a Democrat", circa 1961-1963 (Box 1)
- The Violet, 1963 (Box 1)
- The Violet, 1964 (Box 2)
- Quadrangle, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
- Varsity Basketball Schedule, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
- "The Fales Collection: An Appreciation" by John T. Winterich, 1959 (Box 2)
- Commencement Program, 1960-06-08 (Box 2)
- "Catalogue of the University of the City of New York", 1860 (Box 2)
- Faculty Guide for Washington Square College of Arts and Science, 1963-01 (Box 2)
- Fliers for Huntington Hill Productions, undated (Box 2)
- Perstare Journal, 1958, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
- Historian, 1964-05 (Box 2)
- Heights Students for Human Rights Newsletter, 1960-04-01 (Box 2)
- New York University Official Directory, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
- University College of Arts and Sciences Promotional Publication, undated (Box 2)
- Re-elect Donald J. Sullivan Flier, circa 1960 (Box 2)
- Student Governing Board Censure of Phi Sigma Delta Fraternity, 1960-05 (Box 2)
- Student Governing Board Budget Committee Memoranda, undated (Box 2)
- "Capital Punishment: The Time to Abolish It" by Assemblyman W.G. Kapelman, undated (Box 2)
- Perstare et Praestare Annual Dinner, 1960-04-29 (Box 2)
- Agenda for Lectures Committee, 1959-11-16 (Box 2)
- Booklet: "The Stratford Festival Story, 1953-1964" (Box 2)
- Brochure on Westinghouse Time Capsules, circa 1964 (Box 2)
- University Heights Center Handbook for Residents, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
- Message for Time Capsule from Adlai Stevenson, 1961-07-21 (Box 2)
- Bodley Head Book Catalog, 1964 (Box 2)
- Flier for Commedia dell' Arte Performance of The Doubles According to Plautus, 1964 (Box 2)
- Letter to Dean John W. Knedler from Dan H. Laurence about Shakespeare Committee Activities, 1964-04-30 (Box 2)
- Award to Leslie Yudell for Performance in The Cocktail Party, 1964-05-06 (Box 2)
- Program for Unveiling Bust of Woodrow Wilson in Hall of Fame, 1956-05-20 (Box 2)
- Program for Unveiling Bust for Thomas Jonathan "Stonewall" Jackson in Hall of Fame, 1957-05-19 (Box 2)
- Time Capsule Requests Sent to the White House, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
- Titanium Metals Corporation of America Brochure, undated (Box 2)
- John F. Kennedy Library Exhibit Brochure, undated (Box 2)
- Brochure from National Council on Senior Citizens, undated (Box 2)
- Photograph of Building Workers Outside Begrisch Hall, undated (Box 2)
- Fliers Soliciting Books for Miles College in Birmingham Alabama, undated (Box 2)
- Recording of Metropolitan AIChE convention, Student Chapters, undated; cuid241 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 18-19)
- Recording of Charles Darwin Centennial, Professor Brooke Hindle, Moderator / Professor Abelson [unwound in box], undated; cuid242 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 20-21)
- WNYU Recording of Perstare et Praestare Dinner, President Hester main speaker, Mr. Phil [Price?], 1963-02-26; cuid243 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 22)
- Recording of SGB Meeting (Attendees Listed on Container), 1963-02-26; cuid244 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 23-24)
- Recording of Student Production of H.M.S. Pinafore, 1964-05-09; cuid245 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 25-26)
- Recording of University Heights Debate Council: "Resolved: That the United States Adopt a Program of Compulsory Health Insurance for All Citizens", 1961-05-05; cuid246 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 27)
- Recording of Lecture by Dr. John E. Ricci, Professor of Chemistry; Senior Class Night, May 5, 1961, June 5, 1961; cuid247 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 28-29)
- Recording of Perstare et Praestare Lecture on Shakespeare by Dean John Warren Knedler, Jr; Performance of Aida, 1961; cuid248 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 30-31)
- Recording of Lecture by Professor John Wilkes: "A Walking Tour Through Eighteenth Century London"; Memorial services for President John F. Kennedy held in Gould Memorial Chapel (voice of Dean John Warren Knedler), 1963-11-26; cuid249 (Box 2, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 32)
- Recording of NYU Student Sit-in at Silver Hall, Led by Irv. Rome, 1962-04-12; cuid250 (Box 3, Box Shared University Archives 117, Disk 33)
- Titanium Time Capsule, circa 1964 (Box 4)
- Time capsule plate, 1964 (Box 5)